A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Administrative Functions, RG 4 FA1798
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Communications, 1943-2017; 2; 9.78 Cubic Feet 28 containers
  - Surveys, 2004-2017; 2.8; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
    - Grantee Perception Report, 2014, 2014 August-October (Box 2, Folder 2-4)
      Prepared by The Center for Effective Philanthropy. Labeled Confidential Draft. Also included is a memo of Key Findings and a Complete Set of Grantee Comments and Suggestions by staff member. Included is a Complete Set of Grantee Comments and Suggestions by program officer and/or director, together with memos outlining grant-making activities. This was the fourth Grantee Perception report by CEP for the KF. Also included as an update: a report (dated October 2014) which compares Grantee Perception results against KF's cohort foundations.
    - 2014 Influential Community Leaders Survey, 2014 April-December (Box 2, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5378
      Survey was undertaken by Bendixen & Amandi International. It is the fourth iteration of a research effort to conduct studies of community leaders. Community influencers have in-depth knowledge of Knight programs and share strategic recommendations for future success. The report includes information on each Knight community. There are five versions of the report included.
    - Free Expression on Campus: A survey of U.S. College Students and U.S. Adults, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5851
      Free Expression on Campus: A survey of U.S. College Students and U.S. Adults. Knight Foundation partnered with the Newseum Institute to support a nationally representative survey of U.S. college students. The study sought to better understand how U.S. college students interpret their First Amendment rights, their views of how to balance those rights against other considerations, the impact of their college environment on their views, and the ways in which social media and the press influence expression.
    - Historically Black College and University Students views of free expression on campus, 2016 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 5852
      Historically Black College and University Students views of free expression on campus. As a follow-up to their April report on U.S. college students views of First Amendment rights, Knight Foundation and the Newseum Institute partnered with Gallup to conduct a survey of students at Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs)
    - Future of the First Amendment: 2014 Survey of High School Students and Teachers, 2014 August (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 5853
      Future of the First Amendment: 2014 Survey of High School Students and Teachers. Survey prepared by The Stats Group. Over the past 10 years Knight Foundation has funded five Future of the First Amendment surveys, each probing what American high school students know and think about our most fundamental freedoms.
    - Future of the First Amendment: 2016 Survey of High School Students and Teachers (Box 2, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 5854
      Future of the First Amendment: 2016 Survey of High School Students and Teachers. The survey was conducted by Kenneth Dautrich of The Stats Group. The 2016 "Future of the First Amendment" study marks the sixth time since 2004 that Knight Foundation has surveyed high school students to understand their attitudes toward First Amendment issues.
    - How Youth Navigate The News Landscape, 2017 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 5885
      How Youth Navigate The News Landscape: KF commissioned a series of focus groups with 52 teenagers and young adults from across the United States to learn more about how young people conceptualize and consume news in digital spaces-with a focus on understanding the growing influence of mobile devices, social media and messaging apps.
    - Forecasting Freedom of Information, 2017 March (Box 2, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 5886
      Forecasting Freedom of Information-Why it faces problems-and how experts say they could be solved. KF commissioned this study to better understand the landscape involving public access to government records by gathering information and insights from 336 freedom of information experts-journalists, advocates, records custodians, technology companies, scholars and others.
    - Diversifying Investments: A Study of ownership Diversity in the Asset Management Industry, 2017 May (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Knight File Number - 5888
      Diversifying Investments: A Study of ownership Diversity in the Asset Management. KF commissioned this study to inform the larger discussion unfolding about diversity in the asset management industry.
    - News Editors Survey, 2015 December (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Knight File Number - 5890
      News organizations were asked about types of legal activity they pursued over a two-year period 2014-2015 and provided a range of responses.
    - Understanding Snapchat: Media, Politics and the 2016 Election, 2017 June (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Knight File Number - 5891
      Understanding Snapchat: Media, Politics and the 2016 Election. A survey of Snapchat Users.
    - 2012 Community Leaders Survey, 2012 July-August (Box 2)
      Knight File Number - 5093
      Two copies of a report, prepared by Bendixen & Amandi re: interviews with 793 community leaders from June to August 2012. Major findings include that Knight has achieved extremely high levels of name recognition in its eight resident communities and that significant proress has been made since 2009 on familiarity with the work of the foundation and awareness of the projects Knight is involved in. The survey done in 2009 is compared to the 2012 survey and is broken down by KF community.
    - Grantee Perception Report, 2010 January (Box 2)
      Knight File Number - 5747
      One copy of a report, excerpted for the Board, prepared by the Center for Effective Philanthropy. Key findings provide a summary of grantee responses. Also included are sections, with charts, on Methodology, Measures, Impact, and Relationships. Report is marked CONFIDENTIAL. Also included is a schedule and retreat planning materials for the January 2010 KF CEP Results Sessions staff retreat.
- Finance, 1950-2019; 3; 17.18 Cubic Feet 17 containers
  - Alternative Assets, 1995-2004; 3.1; 0.76 Cubic Feet 2 letter document boxes
    Performance synopses prepared by Cambridge Associates. See also Subseries 4.1 General/Cambridge Associates.
    - Alternative Assets Performance Synopsis, 1995-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
      Knight File Number - 1999-017
    - Alternative Assets Performance Review, 1995-1998 (Box 1)
      Knight File Number - 1885
      Alternative assets performance reviews from Cambridge Associates, 1995-1998.
    - Alternative Assets Performance Review, 2004 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5769
      Alternative assets performance reviews from Cambridge Associates, December 31, 2004.
  - Audited Financial Statements, 1978-2008; 3.2; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    The materials consist of Audited Financial Statements by Ernst and Young.
    - Audited Financial Statement, 1978 December 31-2008 December 31 (Box 1, Folder 1-23)
      Knight File Number - 204
      Ernst & Young annual document includes accountants' report, statement of assets and fund balance, statement of cash receipts and disbursements, and notes to financial statements. 1995 statement also includes a report to the Finance Committee, dated 3/18/96. Missing years: 1992, 1993, 1996, 2002, 2004, 2006, 2007. (See RG1, Audit Committee files for audited financial statements and reports)
  - Budget, 2008-2016; 3.3; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    - 2009 Budget, 2008 November 14-2009 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
      Knight File Number - 4899
      Budget is divided into program areas and initiatives and also contains supplemental information. (3 folders)
    - 2010 Budget, 2009 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
      Knight File Number - 4900
      Budget is divided into program areas and initiatives and also contains supplemental information. (2 folders)
    - 2014 and 2015 Budget Process, 2013 July 23-2014 October 15 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 5599
      Two memos: 1)memo from Controller Elena Stetsenko to KF senior administrators re: budget preparation and timeline for budget reviews and preparation and 2) memo from Terese Coudreaut to administration re: 2015 budget next steps.
    - DCA & Budgeting at Knight: Reference Document, 2015 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 5559
      PowerPoint presentation which explains how staff should characterize Direct Charitable Activity (DCA) in reporting for KF initiative spending in support of KF grant work and its charitable mission. Also included is a section on budget planning.
    - 2017 Budget Process, 2016 August 8-31 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 5741
      Memos from Director of Finance Julio Ocon re: new budget preparation format and timeline for budget reviews.
  - General, 1951-2016; 3.4; 3.13 Cubic Feet 7 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter boxes
    Investment Planning and Manager Selection by Cambridge Associates.
    - Accounting for program initiatives expenses, 1998-2001, 1994-2001 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 6001
      Documents relating the discussion around program initiative expenses (PIE) also known as direct charitable activities (DCA).
    - Investment Planning and Manager Selection, 1985 December 17 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 2632
      Report prepared by Cambridge Associates re: results of review of policy guidelines, proposed asset allocation, proposed manager structure, a draft statement of investment objectives and policies, and information on proposed investment managers.
    - General Ledger, 1983-1990 (Box 1, Folder 8-11)
      Knight File Number - 4805
      Includes financial statements, assets, liabilities, fees, expenses, income and taxes. Also includes a chart of contributors to the Knight Foundation. (4 folders)
    - General Ledger, 1951-1982 (Box 1A, Folder 1-3, Box 1B, Folder 4-6)
      Knight File Number - 4806
      General ledger is subdivided into four sections: Journal, Ledger, Active stock, and Inactive stock. 6 folders.
    - Ennis Knupp Performance Report, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Knight File Number - 4051
      Includes sections on highlights, market environment and performance evaluation for Knight Foundation, Third Quarter 2006.
    - Ennis Knupp Memos to the Investment Committee, 2005 November 30-2006 November 14 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 4050
      Four memos from Ennis Knupp, who were hired to monitor Cambridge Associates work on the Knight Foundation portfolio. Topics include: Ennis Knupp work plan, evaluation of Cambridge, asset allocation analysis, and Cambridge's marketable asset class implementation decisions.
    - Ennis Knupp Performance Report, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      Knight File Number - 4089
      Includes sections on highlights, market environment and performance evaluation for Knight Foundation, Fourth Quarter 2005.
    - Knight Foundation Financial History, 2006 March (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Knight File Number - 3706
      This is a series of charts, graphs and background information assembled by the Finance Department upon the announcement of the sale of Knight Ridder in March, 2006. Included are: a chart of KRI Stock Price vs. Assets and KRI Contributions to Asset Base; statements of assets and fund balance for the Knight Foundation by year; a brief history of the foundation; a history of Knight Ridder from its website; newsclippings and a press release; Knight Foundation historical record of assets and contributions; charts of assets to contributions, and assets vs. contributions; a list of contributions received, 1950-1965; Knight-Ridder year end stock price, 1973-2006 (February); a chart of KRI stock price; a list of KF assets and stock holdings; a chart of total assets vs. KRI investment; financial information re: John S. and James L. Knight estates; and KRI Stock Holdings Analysis. Some of the materials assembled were copied from other KF Archives sources.
    - Knight Foundation Corpus, 2007 November 29 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 4208
      Memo from Juan Martinez to Alberto Ibarguen re: the current value of Knight Foundation's corpus. The purpose of the review was to benchmark portfolio growth versus contributions in reviewing Knight Foundation contributions policy. As of the date, the KF corpus was $2 billion; its portfolio was $2.6 billion. Also included is back up information from Kevin Stephenson of Cambridge Associates.
    - Expenditure Responsibility, 2011 June 15 (Box 7, Folder 5)
      Knight File Number - 5215
      Materials for a discussion on KF Expenditure Responsibility includes: memos re: issues related to expenditure responsibility grants, fiscal agency program at Dade Community foundation, expenditure responsibility tax reporting and an expenditure responsibility worksheet.
    - A Review of Investment Program Governance Practices, Costs and Industry Trends, 2011 August (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Knight File Number - 4941
      Prepared by Hewitt ennisknupp (HEK) for the Knight Foundation, the report is an independent review of the governance model and costs related to the KF investment portfolio. The review also addressed alternatives to the current oversight model, trends within the industry and a discussion of practices of other institutional investors.
    - Knight Foundation Audit Materials, 2012 April 5 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 5197
      Agenda, Cambridge Associates biographies and team structure, and audit support package for a Cambridge site visit by KF associates.
    - Financial Oversight: Lessons about Grant Expenditure Monitoring, 2012-2016 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 5110
      Booklet outlines the lessons learned by KF about financial oversight from managing the Grant Expenditure Monitoring program with accounting firm KPMG and it provides guidance and helpful tools to support others interested in the program. It includes a forward by Juan Martinez. Staff frequently asked questions documents; Grantee frequently asked questions document; GEM workflow (updated)
    - Knight Agency Project Memorandum of Understanding, 2013 February 19 (Box 7, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 5210
      The memorandum sets out the roles and responsibilities of KF and the International Center for Journalists (ICFJ) regarding the Knight Fiscal Agency Project. ICFJ will administer KF grants.
    - Evaluation of ABIA Business Plan, 2013 September 25 (Box 7, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 5380
      The purpose of the report prepared by David Canter was to provide an evaluation of the business plan provided by ABIA as advice and counsel to KF with regards to future grant funding.
    - Implementation of new Finance Systems, 2015-2016 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 5558
      Memos from Juan Martinez and Elena Stetsenko to the KF staff outlining the background and implementation schedule for a new Finance System which will allow for more use of electronic payment and will interact with other KF systems, such as grants management, more easily. Follow up memos chart progress and provide more detailed information on using the new system. Systems include Zendesk, used to manage requests and employee ACH.
    - Cambridge Associates, 1995-2011; 4.1
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2005 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4088
        Includes sections on foundation report, hedge fund report, strategy allocation report, and a non-marketable alternative assets performance report.
      - Annual Analysis of Foundation Investment Pool Returns, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 4374
        Compares and provides statistics for the top U.S. foundations (including KF)
      - Comparative Asset Allocation and Total Return Report, 2006 June 30 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 4376
        Two reports, one for Foundations and one for Nontaxable Portfolios over $1 billion.
      - Manager Meetings, 2006 August 7-9 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 4377
        Agenda, and information on fund managers and companies to be visited by KF and Cambridge personnel.
      - Knight Foundation Hedge Funds Performance and Asset Allocation Report, 2006 March 31 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 4375
        Includes sections on performance and market summary; strategy allocation and management summaries
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2006 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 4053
        Includes sections on foundation report, hedge fund report, and a non-marketable alternative assets performance report.
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Handbook, 2006 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4052
        Includes sections on portfolio overview, historical performance, global equity, fixed income, hedge funds, venture capital/private equity, inflation hedging, real estate, commodities, TIPS, derivatives, manager fees, and contacts.
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Handbook, 2007 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4253
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2007 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4526
      - Knight Foundation Non-Marketable Alternative Assets Performance Review, 2007 June 30 (Box 3, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 5119
        Funding status and performance overview.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2007 September 30 (Box 3, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 5120
        Third quarter investment report, Hedge Fund report, and non-marketable alternative assets performance review as of June 30.
      - Knight Foundation Marketable Alternative Asset Hedge Fund Overview and Non-Marketable Alternative As, 2007 December 6 (Box 3, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 5121
        Discussion materials.
      - Capital Market Commentaries and Flash Returns, 2008 January (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 5122
        Notes on current valuations and investment publications highlights and reports on returns by composite and managers.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2008 March 31 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4325
        Includes sections on: foundation report, hedge fund report, and a non-marketable alternative assets performance report.
      - KF Discussion Materials and London Manager Visits, 2008 April 30 (Box 4, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 5123
        Discussion materials include sections on market update, performance update, frontier markets, Adage, and hedge fund changes.
      - Knight Foundation Investment Performance Report for Second Quarter, 2008 September 9 (Box 4, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4379
        Includes sections on foundation report, hedge fund report, marketable alternative program performance and asset allocation and a non-marketable alternative assets performance report.
      - Knight Foundation Investment Performance Report for Third Quarter, 2008 September 30-November 21 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4422
      - Knight Foundation Discussion Materials, 2008 November 6-7 (Box 4, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 5124
        Contains updates on capital markets, portfolio, performance, hedge fund program, and private equity materials.
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Update and Performance Report, 2008 December 18-31 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 5125
        Includes sections on capital markets, asset allocation, securities lending, November update, and hedge fund flash and foundation report, hedge fund report, and NMAA report.
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Handbook, 2008 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4378
        Includes sections on portfolio overview, historical performance, global equity, fixed income, hedge funds, venture capital/private equity, commodities, real estate, derivatives, manager fees, and contacts.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2009 March 31 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 5126
        Includes sections on foundation report, hedge fund report, and NMAA report.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2009 June 30 (Box 5, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 5127
      - Knight Foundation Discussion Materials, 2009 August 25 (Box 5, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 5129
        Includes sections on capital markets, asset allocation and performance, hedge fund update, non-marketable update, and investment returns.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2009 September 30 (Box 5, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 5128
      - Knight Foundation Discussion Materials, 2010 April 26 (Box 6, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 5132
        Includes sections on portfolio update, minority managers, and capital fund reviews.
      - Knight Foundation Investment Performance Report for Fourth Quarter 2009, 2009 December 31 (Box 6, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4731
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Handbook, 2009 (Box 6, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4576
        Includes sections on portfolio overview, historical performance, global equity, fixed income, hedge funds, venture capital/private equity, commodities, real estate, derivatives, securities lending program, manager fees, and contacts.
      - Knight Foundation Private Equity and Hedge Fund Manager Meetings, New York and Boston, 2010 March 17-March 19 (Box 6, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 5131
        Includes section on each company visited.
      - Knight Foundation Discussion Materials, 2009 October 1 (Box 6, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 5130
        Includes sections on current asset allocation, performance, and capital markets.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2010 June 30 (Box 6, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 5133
        Includes sections on foundation report, hedge fund report, and non-marketable asset allocation report.
      - Knight Foundation Performance Report, 2010 September 30 (Box 6, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 5134
      - Knight Foundation Discussion Materials, 2010 November 2 (Box 7, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 5135
        Includes sections on capital market update, digital media investing, and investment returns and policies.
      - Knight Foundation Investment Performance Report for Fourth Quarter 2010, 2010 December 31 (Box 7, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4864
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Handbook, 2010 (Box 7, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4940
        Includes sections on portfolio overview, historical performance, global equity, fixed income, hedge funds, venture capital/private equity, commodities, real estate, investment policy statement, derivatives, securities lending program, manager fees, and contacts.
      - Knight Foundation Portfolio Handbook, 2011 (Box 7, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4793
        Includes sections on portfolio overview, historical performance, global equity, fixed income, hedge funds, venture capital/private equity, commodities, real estate, investment policy statement, derivatives, manager fees, and contacts.
  - Investment Reference Book, 1995-1997; 3.5; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    Prepared quarterly for the Finance Committee, the books contain general investment objectives and policies, a chronology of investment events, portfolio performance, and reports on investments.
    - Investment Reference Book, 1995 June 1-1997 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 1-6)